A Guide to the Marie-Louise Laleyan Architectural Collection, 1961-2007
Special Collections, Virginia Tech
Special Collections, Virginia Tech
Marie-Louise Laleyan Architectural Collection, 1961-2007
Special Collections, Virginia Tech, Blacksburg, Va.
Laleyan, Marie-Louise, 1935-2014
Ms2013-090
11.3 Cubic Feet 13 boxes
Marie-Louise Laleyan (1935-2014) was a San Francisco based architect with 48 years of experience including 30 years as principal of Laleyan Architects (1977-2007). The collection contains architectural drawings, specifications, construction files, and photographs relating to projects undertaken by Marie-Louise Laleyan (1977-2007) and Laleyan Architects (1972-1977). Photographic record of her U.S. employment (1965-1972) is also present.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Acquisition Information
The Marie-Louise Laleyan Architectural Collection was donated to Special Collections in November 2008.
Biographical Note
Marie-Louise Laleyan (1935-2014) was a San Francisco based architect with 48 years of experience including 30 years as principal of Laleyan Architects (1977-2007), formally Laleyan Associates.
Born and educated in Bulgaria Laleyan arrived in the United States in 1964. Laleyan has practiced architecture in Sofia, Bulgaria; Paris, France; and the United States. Before establishing her own practice she worked with the following firms: Hart & Turner Architects (Sacramento, CA), Richard Neutra (Los Angeles, CA), and the San Francisco, CA firms of Claude Oakland and Associates, Anshen & Allen, Mario J. Ciamp, FAIA, and Paffard Keatinge Clay.
An active member of the American Institute of Architects (AIA) she has served on the Northern California Chapter's Board of Directors, as co-chairperson of the national AIA Task Force of Women in Architecture, and coauthor of the AIA Affirmative Action Plan. She was also a founder of the Bay Area's Organization of Women in Architecture (OWA) and has represented the interests of women architects at numerous conferences and seminars.
The establishment of Laleyan Associates in 1977 was the culmination of a lifelong career intention and in her words a 'family tradition.' Laleyan was committed to keeping the firm small so that she would be able to provide quality service and personal attention to each project and client. Projects undertaken by Laleyan Architects included light commercial, medical, institutional, residential, and public buildings with construction costs ranging from $25,000-3.4 million dollars.
In 2001, Laleyan began providing Physical Needs Assessments (PNA) and Construction Monitoring services for the California Housing Finance Agency (CHFA), a state housing acquisition lender to non-profit and for profit developers.
Laleyan died on January 21, 2014.
Scope and Content
The collection contains architectural drawings, specifications, construction files, and photographs relating to projects undertaken by Marie-Louise Laleyan (1977-2007) and Laleyan Architects (1972-1977). Photographic record of her U.S. employment (1965-1972) is also present.
Adjunct Descriptive Data
Separated Materials
Materials related to Illinois architect Bertha Y. Whitman were removed from the Laleyan collection and placed in Ms2009-054 IAWA Small Collections under Whitman's name. (3/2009)
Index Terms
Subjects::
Architecture; History of Women in Architecture; International Archive of Women in Architecture (IAWA); Women -- History; Women-owned architectural firms
Occupations:
Architects
Contents List
- Professional Papers, 1972-1994
  - Articles, Presentations, Press Releases, Thought Pieces, and Writings, 1977-1986 (Box 5)
  - Project List, 1972-2007 (Box 5)
  - Request for Proposal (RFP) West Block Studios - TNDC (Tenderloin Neighborhood Development Corporation, November 15, 2004 (Box 5)
- Project Records, 1972-2000
  Scope and Content
  The following is a list of architectural projects and services carried out by Marie L. Laleyan (1972-1973) and her firm Laleyan Architects (1977-2006).
  Arrangement
  The Project Index is a way to organize the various formats of architectural records from the same project. The index is arranged alphabetically by Job Number and contains information, where available, about the location, date, project type, architect, collaborators, photographers, and formats for each project in the collection. Project Index A Summary of the Project Index is listed below.
  - Marie L. Laleyan Project Records, 1972-1973
    - #101 - Duplex, San Rafael (Mr. and Mrs. Al Valenzano), 1972 (Box 1, Box 9)
    - #102 - 4141 Geary Medical Building, Suite 324, 1973 (Box 1, Box 9)
    - #103 - Alterations to Residence and Office, San Francisco (Mr. and Mrs. Gerald Stein), 1973 (Box 1, Box 9)
    - #104 - 4141 Geary Medical Building, Suite 324, 1973 (Box 1, Box 9)
    - #105 - 4141 Geary Medical Building, Suite 419/420, 1973 (Box 1, Box 9)
  - Laleyan Architects Project Records, 1977-2000
    - AGS81 - AGS Graphics and Systems, 1981 (Box 1)
    - CCR83 - Civic Center Residence Hotel Rehab (CCR-G programming) [8 folders], 1980-1986 (Box 1)
    - CCR85 - Civic Center Residence Hotel Rehab III [5 folders], 1985-1986 (Box 1, Box 6)
    - CIV83 - Medical Suite Addition, for Arthur Civello, MD,, 1983 (Box 1)
    - CLH84 - California League for Handicapped, Preliminary Studies, 1983-1984 (Box 1)
    - DB-102/79 - Bloomfield Residence, Jack and Carol Bloomfield [2 folders],, 1979-1981 (Box 1, Box 9, Box 12)
    - DB-103/78 - Single Family Residence, Mr and Mrs. James Cunningham, 5121 Cabrillo, 1978-1979 (Box 1, Box 9, Box 12)
    - DB-203/78 - Single Family Residence, Steve and Irene Marciel, 4980 Discovery Point, 1979-1980 (Box 1, Box 9, Box 12)
    - DB-303/79 - Davis Residence, Robert and Karen Davis, 1260 Discovery Bay Road, 1979-1980 (Box 1, Box 9, Box 12)
    - DB-403/80 - Residence, North Point, 1980-1981 (Box 1, Box 12)
    - DB-503/80 - House, Discovery Bay Blvd., 1980-1981 (Box 1, Box 12)
    - DB-603/80 - House, Willow Lake Road [not built], 1981 (Box 1, Box 12)
    - DLT99 - Dalt Hotel Rehabilitation [9 folders], 1999-2000 (Box 1, Box 8)
    - DOE78 - Dental Office, Kira Eldemir, DDS [2 folders], 1978-1981, 1987 (Box 2, Box 9, Box 12)
    - ELD81 - Flats-Rehab Studio (Box 2)
    - ELD85 - Remodeling of Residence for Kira Eldemir, DDS (Box 2, Box 9)
    - ELD87 - Dental Office Addition for Kira Eldemir, DDS (Box 2)
    - ENN77 - Enna Residence Addition, 1977 (Box 2)
    - FRK89 - St. Boniface Friars Kitchen Renovation, 1989-1990 (Box 2, Box 6)
    - HFC84 - Howard Street Apartments, 1040-42 Howard Street, San Francisco [6 folders], 1985-1991 (Box 2, Box 10)
    - KLM86 - Klimm Apartments Rehab [17 folders], 1985-1989 (Box 2, Box 8)
    - KPR86 - Condominium Remodel, for Dobri Kiprov, MD - preliminary only, 1986-1987 (Box 3)
    - KPR87 - Penthouse Remodel for Dobri Kiprov, MD, 1986-1987 (Box 3)
    - LAA88 - Laleyan Associates Architects (Box 5)
    - LAZ81 - Union Street Shops [2 folders], 1980-1982 (Box 3, Box 9, Box 10)
    - LAZ94 - Roof Parapet Reinforcement, Presidio Heights Apartments [2 folders], 1993-1995 (Box 3, Box 8)
    - LPPI84 - Langley Porter Psychiatric Institute (UCSF) - Children's Wing [6 folders], 1983-1989 (Box 3, Box 8)
    - MLR91 - House Remodel (Miller), 1991 (Box 3)
    - PUD-B/81 - Planned Unit Development, Brentwood, 1981-1982 (Box 3, Box 9, Box 12)
    - RCC88 - Chiang Flats (exterior treatment consultation) (Box 3)
    - RCH83 - Russ Apartment Building Rehab: pre-programming only
    - SMO85 - Serramonte Center Space E-460, studies for Bay Area Pediatrics Group, 1984-1985 (Box 3)
    - SRR78 - Salvatore Residence Rehab (Box 3, Box 12)
    - SSG89/SSG91 - Southland/Southgate Housing Development (CHFA 91-036-N) [17 folders], 1986, 1991-1994 (Box 3, Box 7)
    - T&B82 - Ron Greenspan VW for T&B Interior Designers (Box 3, Box 10)
    - TDE82 - Yosemite Apartment Building, 1982-1986 (Box 3, Box 9)
    - TDL82 - Sierra Madre Apartment Building (Box 4, Box 9)
    - TIM90 - Residence for Tim Fagan, Alta Hills, 1990-2000 (Box 4, Box 8)
    - TMR81 - Tomer Residence Remodel, 1981 (Box 4, Box 10)
    - UNY81 - The Unitery, Early Child Education Center, 1981 (Box 4, Box 10)
    - WBL95 - Plaza and Ramona Apartments WBL-P & WBL-R, 1995-1996 (Box 4, Box 11)
    - WBR91 - Webber Unit Remodel, 1991 (Box 4, Box 8)
  - California Housing Finance Agency, 2003-2006
    Historical Note
    Projects with the California Housing Finance Agency are presented as a representation of services offered by Laleyan Architects and are to be used for general information only. Laleyan Architects was not the architect for these projects.
    - CHFA 00-021-N - Thomas Paine Square Apartments, 2003 (Box 5)
    - CHFA 01-028-N - Roberts Avenue Senior Housing, 2003 (Box 5)
    - CHFA 03-001-N - Surf Apartments, 2003-2004 (Box 5)
    - CHFA 03-028-N - Plaza de las Flores, 2006 (Box 5)
    - CHFA 05-003-N - Hillvale Glen Apartments, Physical Needs Assessment, 2005 (Box 5)
    - CHFA 05-003-N - Padre Apartments Community, 2004 (Box 5)
  - Drawings (Box 6-12)
    Drawings are present for the following projects: #101, #102, #103, #104, #105, CCR85, DB-102, DB-103, DB-203, DB-303, DB-406, DB-503, DB-603, DLT99, DOE78, ENN77, FRK89, HFC84, KLM86, LAZ81, LAZ94, LPPI84, PUB-B/81, SRR78, SSG91, T&B82, TDE82, TDL82, TIM90, TMR81, UNY81, WBL95, and WBR91. Drawings are in boxes 6-12. The locations are tied to the relevant projects in the Marie L. Laleyan Project Records subseries and Laleyan Architects Project Records subseries.
  - Reduced Drawings (Box 5, Folder 19)
- Project Photographs
  - Affordable Multi-Family Housing Rehabilitation Projects (2 Photo Albums), 2002 (Box 5, Folder 17-18)
  - Firm Projects Photo Album (Box 5, Folder 16)
  - Marie-Louise Laleyan Employment in the USA (2 folders), 1965-1976 (Box 5, Folder 14-15)
    Projects include work with Richard and Dion Neutra, Los Angeles (1967-1969) and Paffard Keatinge Clay, San Francisco (1969-1971)
  - Project Negatives (Box 5)
    Negatives are available for the following projects: DB103, DB203; DB303; DOE78.
    Negatives are in box 5. The location is tied to the relevant projects in the Marie L. Laleyan Project Records subseries and Laleyan Architects Project Records subseries.
  - Presentation Boards (Box 13)
  - Slides (Box 5)
    Slides are present for the following projects: DB102, DB103, DB203, DB303, DB403, DOE78, ELD87, HFC84, KLM86, LAA88, LAZ81, SSG91, TDE82, and TDL82.
    Slides are in box 5. The location is tied to the relevant projects in the Marie L. Laleyan Project Records subseries and Laleyan Architects Project Records subseries.
    - Golden Sands Bulgaria, 1961